Finding Aid for the Edwin Bower Hesser Papers LSC.1071
UCLA Library Special Collections
Edwin Bower Hesser papers
1917-1958
1920-1950
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hesser, Edwin Bower
LSC.1071
14.25 Linear Feet (28 boxes and 30 oversize boxes)
Edwin Bower Hesser (1893-1962) was a prominent photographer who worked in New York and Los Angeles during the golden age of Hollywood and developed his own color photography system known as Hessercolor. The bulk of the collection consists of photographic materials such as negatives, prints, transparencies, and periodicals featuring Hesser's work. The collection also includes paper materials, such as miscellaneous manuscripts, business papers and journals.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Material in box 55 contain cellulose nitrate photographic negatives unavailable for access. These nitrate negatives must be digitized in order to be available for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Wien, Sales, and Kaplan, 1969.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942331393606533
Biography
Edwin Bower Hesser was born Karl Edwin Hesser on April 23, 1893 in Jersey City, New Jersey. Born into a theatrical family with a theatrical company manager as a father and an art teacher as a mother, Hesser became involved in theatre, drawing, sculpture, painting, and commercial photography at the age of 17. In 1914, he married Rhea May Reed in Aberdeen, South Dakota while managing a theatrical troupe. In 1917, Hesser wrote the story for a theatrical film entitled For the Freedom of the World and wrote, produced, and directed The Triumph of Venus that same year.
In 1918, Hesser was commissioned as Captain in the Photographic Section of the U.S. Army Signal Corps where he reorganized the motion picture photographic division of the Army. Later that year, Hesser received an honorable discharge and moved to New York City. He also separated from his wife Rhea, who later divorced him in 1920. Hesser was employed as a writer and producer by First National Pictures, and then started his own independent photographic studio. Hesser moved to Los Angeles in 1920 to continue to work for First National Pictures, where he became the portrait photographer for the studio's stars (he still maintained his photo studio in New York). That same year, he also started up a second independent photography studio in Los Angeles while working as a photographer for the L.A. Examiner.
In his independent photography studios Hesser focused mainly on calendar pictures and art illustrations for major photographic magazines, and continued his portraiture work of theatrical and Hollywood personalities. In 1925, he began his own magazine entitled Arts Monthly Pictorial, which featured his photographic work of nude and semi-nude women. He married his second wife, Margaret Watts, in 1931, but she left and divorced him in 1933 to marry Ridgeway Callow. On July 1, 1934, Hesser married his former model Eve, who became a major collaborator in his photographic business. Eve's father, Clarence Cunningham, became the chief financier of Hesser's business and helped him finance the development of his own three-color system known as Hessercolor. This color system involved three separate negatives that captured three color values. Gelatin prints (yellow, cyan, and magenta) were then made from the negatives and layered together to create one color print. Hessercolor was used on the sets of early Technicolor films such as La Cucaracha (1934) and Becky Sharp (1935).
After loosing the battle to Kodak for the use of his color system in World War II photography, Hesser's career began to focus on war-time inventions such as an aerial color camera and water and flame proof insulation for military airplanes. He continued his magazine and fashion photography into the 1940s, shooting on Kodachrome, and also began to do family and individual portraiture for hire. Throughout his life, Hesser experienced numerous health problems. He died August 7, 1962.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Edwin Bower Hesser's negatives, assorted paper materials, transparencies, and photographic prints documenting his 40-year career as a photographer and inventor. Of particular interest are photographic prints of Hollywood personalities such as Mary Astor, Joan Blondell, Mary Pickford, Douglas Fairbanks, Loretta Young, Claudette Colbert, Lupe Valez, Janet Gaynor, and Joan Crawford (among many others); prints of the experimental coloring process "Hessercolor"; prints of semi-nude, nude, and erotic modeling; hand colored prints; Hesser's periodical Arts Monthly Pictorial; and assorted advertising and modeling transparencies and prints. The collection also contains a voluminous assortment of negatives of portraits and head shots, as well as miscellaneous manuscript materials such as letters, photographic elements and writings by Eve Hesser, workbooks, inventions, photo shoot posing ideas, periodicals, and documentation related to the development and patent of the Hessercolor process.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Negatives, ca. 1920-1946 (13.5 boxes, 0.5 oversize box), subseries A-B as follows:
A. Named subjects
B. Anonymous subjects
Assorted paper materials, 1917-1958 (6.5 boxes, 4.5 oversize boxes), subseries A-C as follows:
A. Miscellaneous
B. Periodicals
C. Posing ideas
Color transparencies (1.5 boxes)
Hollywood personalities, ca. 1925-1938 (0.5 box, 2 oversize boxes)
Prints, ca. 1920-1945 (6 boxes, 19 oversize boxes), subseries A-D as follows:
A. Large Hessercolor
B. Large black and white
C. Small black and white
D. Small Hessercolor.
Photographers -- United States -- Archives.; Photographs.; Hesser, Edwin Bower--Archives.
- Negatives, ca. 1920-1946; 13.5 boxes, 0.5 oversize box
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of black and white negatives and test prints of various sizes shot by Edwin Bower Hesser. Arranged in subseries A-B as follows:
  A. Named subjects, ca. 1942-1946
  B. Anonymous subjects, ca. 1920-1946.
  - A. Named subjects, ca. 1942-1946
    This subseries consists of black and white negatives featuring portraits of named models and persons photographed by Edwin Bower Hesser. These negatives include women, men, and children in casual, semi-formal, and formal attire; nude, semi-nude, and erotic modeling women; women in costume and festive attire; various animals; women in bathing suits; women in winter clothes; men in military uniforms; couples; models with various props; theatrical and film scenes; and shots of Edwin Bower Hesser and his wife Eve. Files are arranged alphabetically according to the surname of featured subject(s).
    - Agguirre, Jaoquin, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in sweater posing and holding tennis racket.
    - Albert, David and Charlotte (tests), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of couple in formal attire.
    - Alice- Bank of America, West Hollywood, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman in casual attire.
    - Alvord, Bette Jeanne, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling hunting outfit, bathing suit, and Latin- ruffled tube top.
    - Anderson, Lieutenant, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in military uniform. Includes test prints.
    - Armstrong, Alma, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in business suit and casual attire.
    - Austin, Renee, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in business suit and bathing suit with beach ball.
    - Baker, Ann, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling flower print vest, formal attire, ruffled dress, and bathing suit with props. Includes test prints.
    - Barnes, Barbra, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait or head shot of young woman modeling sequenced- strapless dress and robe.
    - Baron, Nancy, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling bathing suit, sweater, and formal attire.
    - Basco, Theal, 1945 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in suit. Includes test prints.
    - Beck, Mrs., ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling bathing suit, formal attire including fancy hats, and western wear. Includes test prints.
    - Bedell, Nelle, 1944 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young girl. Includes test prints.
    - Biber, Kitty, 1944 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in casual attire posing and laying down. Includes test prints.
    - Bond, Mr. and Mrs., ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of elderly couple in formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Bower, Toni, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman in formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Bowman, Bob, 1946 January (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bradbary, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      4 x 5" black and white exterior portraits and head shots of a young woman in strapless ruffled dress. Includes test prints.
    - Brandy (Max Kingslittle's dog), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait or head shot of young woman holding dog outdoors.
    - Brewer, Mrs., 1946 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of older woman in formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Brinkman, Nancy, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling semi-nude in a sheet and lingerie, formal attire, and Latin-ruffled dress.
    - Brooks, Jo Ann, 1946 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman in business suit.
    - Browne, Doris, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling low-cut ruffled dress and casual attire.
    - Bruno, Mary, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling hooded raincoat and low-cut ruffled top.
    - Buckswell, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling sweater and bathing suit. Includes test print.
    - Buferd, Marilyn, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling spaghetti strap top and formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Camillia and Sister (dog), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young girl and dachshund.
    - Chandler, Janis, 1945 December (Box 1, Folder 28)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling formal attire, flower-print dress, and Latin- ruffled dress. Also includes shot of model outdoors holding three dogs. Includes test prints.
    - Chapelle, Jean Dela, 1946 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman in girl scouts uniform holding fishing pole.
    - Chedister, Anne in Long Beach, CA, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling strapless dress, formal attire, and hat.
    - Chevalis, Maxine, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling semi-nude in a sheet and lingerie. Includes test prints.
    - Children's Guild, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of a young girl. Envelope reads: "Melody, Lady Petty, Knittel (valley)." Includes test prints
    - Cleo, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      4 x 5" portrait or head shot of woman in plaid and flower print blouse.
    - Clive, Henry, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of older man in suit smoking cigar.
    - Clive, Luther and Sylvia Boldwin Muller, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in military uniform embracing and kissing a woman with straps on dress falling down. Includes test prints.
    - Coffey, Mrs., ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Collister (tests), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling bathing suit, button-up coat, and casual attire.
    - Colonel - Camp Haan, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man dressed in military uniform. Envelope reads; "Aid to General Nichols, friend of Capt. Robinson." Includes test prints.
    - Conway, Lorraine - East Menu, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in formal attire.
    - Corelli, Lutus, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling semi-nude in a sheet and robe. Includes test prints.
    - Craig, Pauline, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in low-draping sheet, business suit, casual attire. Includes test prints.
    - Crampton, Marjorie, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of older woman in fur coat and hat. Includes test prints.
    - Cummeker, Kay, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling fishnet hose laying down with legs propped up against wall.
    - Dallmeir, Fern, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling bathing suit, casual attire, Latin-ruffled dress, veiled dress, and semi-nude in a sheet.
    - Damon, Marge and Bob, 1944 August 16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of older couple in formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Darin, Dr., 1944 October 12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots older, man with a moustache in suit. Includes test prints.
    - Davis, Mrs. and baby, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait or head shot of woman holding baby in bonnet.
    - Dean, Dell, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling nude on stool, low-cut ruffled dress, and sweater.
    - Diamonds, Beverly, 1944 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of curly haired young girl in hat and dress.
    - Dobson, Dottie, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in casual attire.
    - Donna, ca. 1943-19545 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling semi nude in sheet and sweater.
    - Dumpsey, Mrs., ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of woman modeling at the beach in bathing suit. Includes shots of other models in a group.
    - Easen, Fay, 1945 March 18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling in low-cut dress. Includes test prints.
    - Elaise, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of woman modeling bathing suit.
    - Eleanor, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      4 x 5" black and white shot of woman modeling business attire outdoors.
    - Elliot, Skippy, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      4 x 5" black and white shot of woman in business attire in front of tree and leaves backdrop. Includes test prints.
    - Emcke, Camilla, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots.
    - Erickson, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man with moustache modeling western shirt, topless, smoking pipe, and overcoat. Includes test prints.
    - Eunce, Camilla and Flicka (dog), 1944 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young girl posing with dachshund. Includes test prints.
    - Evans, Miss and Henry (dog), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of woman modeling casual attire outside with shaggy dog.
    - Fawcett, Mr., 1944 September 27 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Feiler, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young girl in plaid dress crying and upset. Includes shot of her with older man.
    - Feiler, Morton (baby), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of infant sitting on a bed.
    - Ferguson, Jean, 1945 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Fisher, Miss, 1946 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling Latin-ruffled dress and head scarf.
    - Flash tests at night, 1945 June (Box 2, Folder 26)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling business dress in front of zebra backdrop.
    - Forester, Cay, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling strapless ruffled dress, semi-formal attire, and casual attire. Includes shots of woman lying down.
    - Funal, Bovis, 1945 March (Box 2, Folder 28)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in plaid suit. Includes test prints.
    - Gibson, Wynne, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shot of woman modeling legs through formal dress while sitting on stool.
    - Gilbert, Helen, 1944 March 28 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling semi-formal attire while sitting and laying down. Includes test prints.
    - Godwin, Mrs., 1944 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman in semi-formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Good Night Ladies, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      4 x 5" black and white shots from a stage play featuring John Hubbard, Russ Brown, Claire Mead, and Fred Sherman. Includes action shots and portraits of characters.
    - Gordon, Sidney, 1943 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in military uniform and suit smoking pipe.
    - Gorman, Mrs., 1944 April 27 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling butterfly print dress, fur coat, and formal attire while laying down. Includes test prints.
    - Grancell, Sherman, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of couple dressed in business attire.
    - Green, Linda, 1945 June 14 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young girl outdoors and in the studio. Includes test prints.
    - Gresham, Ensign, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in military uniform.
    - Guile, Miss, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling low-cut formal attire, short festive dress, and business attire with flower in hair. Includes test prints.
    - Gulike, Jeannie, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling formal gown with veil, laying semi-nude on couch with gloves on. Includes test prints.
    - Gunneler, Kay, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of woman modeling burlesque lingerie type of attire while leaning on stool.
    - Hamilton, Adele, 1944 July 25 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling semi-nude, lying down and standing covered by a large book. Also includes shots modeling bathing suit and casual attire. Includes test prints.
    - Hannock, 1946 July 12 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of man in white collared shirt, suit, and topless. Includes test prints.
    - Harris, June, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling low-cut formal attire and casual attire. Includes test prints.
    - Hartzell, Captain, 1944 September 26 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait or head shot of man in military uniform.
    - Haver, Ronnalee, 1944 August 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling bathing suit and formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Hesser, Bob, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of a photographic portrait of a man in military flight uniform.
    - Hesser, Edwin, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait of Hesser in suit.
    - Hesser, Edwin and Eve, 1944 January (Box 3, Folder 16)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of Hessers passionately embracing and kissing, also includes solo shots.
    - Hesser, Edwin and Eve with "H.C.", 1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of Hesser and wife with man named "H.C." Includes test prints.
    - Hesser, Eve (1 of 2), 1944 December 4 and 1944 January (Box 3, Folder 18)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of Hesser modeling various outfits. Includes test prints.
    - Hesser, Eve (2 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of Hesser modeling various outfits.
    - Hill Family - Paula, Levy, Corelli, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman modeling low-cut gown and casual attire. Includes test prints.
    - Hill, Corelli, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of middle-aged couple in formal attire. Includes test prints.
    - Hopskins, Sue, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of young woman in Asian-silk top, casual attire, semi-formal attire, and strapless dress. Includes test prints.
    - Hubbard, Carol, 1945 September (Box 3, Folder 23)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling formal and casual attire. Includes shots of model semi-nude laying on couch.
    - Hubbard, John, July 15 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of Hubbard with 3 women from stage play. Includes test prints.
    - Hubbard, Mary Jane, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling business attire, formal attire, semi-nude in sheet and bra. Includes test prints.
    - Hunneker, Kay, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling wrap top and underwear.
    - Immerman, Mrs., ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots. Includes test prints.
    - Jackson, Virginia, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling western attire.
    - Jarvis, Louise, 1945 February 23 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of woman modeling business attire and fur coat and hat. Includes test prints.